Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Labor Movement Serials WAG.345
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Labor Movement Serials
1891-2012
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Communications Workers of America
National Maritime Union of America
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
International Brotherhood of Teamsters
United Federation of Teachers
United Steelworkers of America
Co-operative League of America
Hotel & Restaurant Employees and Bartenders International Union
WAG.345
200.5 Linear Feet in 25 record cartons, 4 manuscript boxes, and 150 oversize flat boxes
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Labor Movement Serials groups 2,116 titles published between 1891 and 2012 mainly chronicling the labor movement in the 20th century, originally received by the Tamiment Library through subscriptions, donations, and as part of archival collections. The majority of the collection consists of incomplete runs of newspapers, newsletters, bulletins, and mailings distributed by unions, national and local chapters of labor organizations, rank and file groups, government agencies, and advocacy groups. The serials document the activities of individual unions and organizations as well as the trajectory of the labor movement more broadly, with discussions on labor law and government policy, relationships and solidarity between affinity groups, and the concerns of particular constituencies of workers. Serials in this collection range from official publications and proceedings regularly distributed by large, AFL-CIO-affiliated organizations to pamphlets and printed matter informally circulated by organizers to announce meetings and actions. In addition to serials chronicling the labor movement in the United States, there are significant quantities of material relating to labor conditions in Europe and Canada.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to users without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection combines serials relating to the labor movement drawn from two discrete groups of material held by the Tamiment Library. The first was a partially inventoried backlog of serials, received by the library through donations, subscriptions, and in archival collections. The second group consisted of around 1,700 serials, newspapers, and magazines, organized by title as an artificial collection, referred to as Periodicals.001 or Boxed Newspapers. This material was combined, inventoried, and arranged and described in subject-based categories in 2017.
Arrangement
This collection imposes an artificial arrangement on a range of disparate material separated from the order in which it was originally received at Tamiment Library. The material is separated into five series, dividing serials into groups of topically similar material. The first series largely collects serials issued by labor unions, grouping this material into 12 narrower subseries, according to a union's trade or constituency. The remaining series collect concentrations of similar types of material, for example labor newspapers, or material originating from outside the United States. Within each series, material is arranged at the file level, in alphabetical order by publishing organization. Where possible issues of each publication are organized chronologically, grouped by year. Each title is listed alongside its publishing organization and city of origin, where this information is available.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to the fragile nature of certain original materials, researchers may be required to consult microfilm copies, preservation photocopies, or digital images of material in this collection.
Scope and Contents
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Labor Movement Serials groups 2,116 titles published between 1891 and 2012 mainly chronicling the labor movement in the 20th century, originally received by the Tamiment Library through subscriptions, donations, and as part of archival collections.
The majority of the collection consists of incomplete runs of newspapers, newsletters, bulletins, and mailings distributed by unions, national and local chapters of labor organizations, rank and file groups, government agencies, and advocacy groups. The serials document the activities of individual unions and organizations -- meetings, elections, appointments, negotiations -- as well as the fluctuating trajectories of the labor movement more broadly, with discussions on labor law and government policy, relationships and solidarity between affinity groups, and the concerns of particular constituencies of workers. Serials in this collection range from official publications and conference proceedings regularly distributed by large, AFL-CIO-affiliated organizations to pamphlets and printed matter informally circulated by organizers to announce meetings and actions. Among the larger organizations represented in this collection are the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America; the Communication Workers of America; the American Federation of Teachers; the International Brotherhood of Teamsters; and Teamsters for a Democratic Union, as well as prominent labor coalitions in New York State like the United Federation of Teachers and the New York City Central Labor Council. Notable titles include American Postal Worker; Labor Chronicle; United Labor Action; United Teacher; Working Teamster; The NMU Pilot; Solidarity, issued by the Labor Committee of the New York Students for a Democratic Society; and the Philadelphia Workers' Organizing Committee's Organizer.
The trades and professions represented in this collection form a comprehensive cross-section of organized labor in the 20th century, encompassing bulletins from unions and rank and file groups representing the building trades, communications workers, public employees, transport employee unions, education and entertainment unions, farmworkers and longshoremen, retail and service workers, and coalitions representing demographics working across different sectors, for example the Jewish Labor Committee.
In addition to the material documenting the activities of unions in America, the collection also includes a series dedicated to labor research and history, and a collection of trade journals and labor newspapers. Around 300 titles originate from outside the United States, with significant quantities of Canadian and European publications, often representing international bodies or research groups discussing labor policy. No complete runs of publications are contained herein, and generally only a handful of issues of each publication are held.
Existence and Location of Copies
In some instances researchers may be required to consult microfilm copies of material held in this collection. Information on microfilm copies is included below each title listing.
Labor movement -- United States -- History; Industrial relations -- United States -- Periodicals.; Labor laws and legislation -- United States.; Labor unions -- Organizing -- United States.
- Series I: Labor unions and organizations, 1891-2012; 188.25 Linear Feet in 24 record cartons and 139 oversize flat boxes
  Scope and Contents
  This series collects 1,723 publications -- serials, journals, magazines, newsletters, newspapers, bulletins, pamphlets -- issued by labor unions and other related organizations. The majority of the series collects weekly or monthly bulletins distributed by local chapters of unions documenting local activities, wider national efforts, and the lives of union members.
  Arrangement
  The material in this series is divided into 12 subseries: Subseries I.A: Building Trades; Subseries I.B: Communication Workers; Subseries I.C: Constituency Groups; Subseries I.D: Co-operatives; Subseries I.E: Education Workers; Subseries I.F: Entertainment; Subseries I.G: Farmworkers and Agricultural Unions; Subseries I.H: Maritime Workers; Subseries I.I: Labor Coalitions and Organizations; Subseries I.J: Public Employees; Subseries I.K: Retail and Service Workers; and Subseries I.L: Transportation Workers. These series group together material issued by organizations operating in similar trades -- educators; entertainment workers; public employees -- or, in the case of Series I, Subseries C, group organizations uniting members around identity or common interest. A taxonomy used within Tamiment Library to structure access to its collections, delineating affinities between different industries and unions in detail, was adapted to structure the 12 subseries of Series I.
  - Subseries I.A: Building Trades, 1918-2004; 16 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons and 11 oversize boxes
    This series collects publications issued by construction and building trades unions, mainly through the 20th century. Large organizations of painters, molders, miners, chemical workers, and engineers -- including the American Federation of Technical Engineers, and the United Steelworkers of America -- are represented at both the national and local level. Smaller organizations and rank and file groups are represented by newsletters circulated to raise awareness around topics including health issues among miners (Miner's Voice; Progressive Miner; Straight Track); safety regulations governing the construction industry (variants of the widely distributed Hard Hat News; Rusty Nail; Construction Labor News); and corruption in Local 282 of the International Brotherhood of Teamsters (published by Fear of Reprisal Ends).
    - Engineers' Outlook: American Federation of Technical Engineers, Washington, DC, 1951 (Box 41, Folder 1)
    - Tech Talk Monthly Bulletin: American Federation of Technical Engineers - Architectural & Engineering Guild, Local 66, New York, NY, 1971 (Box 41, Folder 2)
    - Federal Newsletter: American Federation of Technical Engineers, AFL-CIO, Washington, DC, 1972 (Box 41, Folder 3)
    - Project: American Federation of Technical Engineers, AFL-CIO - Port Authority Division of the Architectural and Engineering Guild, Local 66, New York, NY, 1968-1970 (Box 172, Folder 3)
    - Union Democracy in the Construction Trades: Association for Union Democracy, circa 1970s (Box 41, Folder 4)
    - Technician: Association of Civilian Technicians, Rockville, MD, 1981-1983 (Box 83, Folder 10)
    - Rebel: Association of Western Pulp and Paper Workers, Portland, OR, 1974 (Box 41, Folder 5)
    - Construction Labor News: Bette Dravis, San Jose, CA, 1984 (Box 44, Folder 1)
    - Marine Engineer: Brotherhood of Marine Engineers, Brooklyn, NY, 1957 (Box 41, Folder 6)
    - Rank and File Painters Bulletin/Rank and File Painter: Brotherhood of Painters - Local 848, New York, NY, 1947 (Box 44, Folder 2-3)
    - Report: Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators & Paperhangers of America, 1947 (Box 41, Folder 7)
    - News for You: Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators and Paperhangers of America, Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators and Paperhangers of America, 1960 (Box 41, Folder 8)
    - 282 Teamster: Building Material Local 282, Lake Success/Elmont, NY, 1987-1991 (Box 41, Folder 9)
    - News and Opinion: Building Trades Employers, Association of the City of New York, New York, NY, 1954 (Box 41, Folder 10)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Due to the fragile condition of this material, access may be supervised or restricted.
    - Construction Labor Report: Bureau of National Affairs, Inc., Washington, DC, 1973 (Box 41, Folder 11)
    - Miner's Voice: Butte Miners' Union Local No. 1 - International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers (C.I.O.), Butte, MT, 1947 (Box 44, Folder 4)
    - Hard Hat: Center for Practical Education, San Francisco, CA, 1994-1998 (Box 41, Folder 12-13)
    - SWEAT: Center for Practical Education, San Francisco, CA, 1997 (Box 41, Folder 14)
    - Riveting News: Cleveland Hard Hatted Women, Cleveland, OH, 1990 (Box 41, Folder 15)
    - Coal Mining Women's Support Team News: Coal Employment Project, Knoxville, TN, 1989 (Box 41, Folder 16)
    - Miner's Voice: Committee for Miners' Rights, Morgantown, WV, 1969-1973 (Box 44, Folder 5)
    - Council Compass: Council of Western Electric Technical Employees, Newark, NJ, 1948 (Box 41, Folder 17)
    - Steel Labor's Road to Economic Security, Peace, and Democracy: A Communist Viewpoint: CPUSA, New York, NY, 1953 (Box 41, Folder 18)
    - Steel City Organizer: CPUSA (M-L) at US Steel, Gary Work, Gary, IN, 1979 (Box 41, Folder 19)
    - Building Tradesman: D.C. No. 9 - United Rank and File, New York, NY, 1949 (Box 44, Folder 6)
    - Carpenter: District Council of Carpenters, New York, NY, 1984-2004 (Box 44, Folder 7)
    - Guild Newsletter: Engineering & Professional Guild, Local 66, IFPTE, AFL-CIO, New York, NY, 1976 (Box 41, Folder 20)
    - F.O.R.E. Bulletin: Fear of Reprisal Ends, 1981 (Box 41, Folder 21)
    - 282 F.O.R.E. Newsletter: Fear of Reprisal Ends Local 282, Flushing/W. Islip, NY, 1977-1981 (Box 41, Folder 22)
    - FORE: Fear of Reprisal Ends Local 282, Flushing, NY, 1981 (Box 41, Folder 23)
    - Supervisor: Foreman's Association of America, Detroit, MI, 1945 (Box 41, Folder 24)
    - Glass Forum: Glaziers Local 1087, New York, NY, 1994 (Box 41, Folder 25)
    - Steel on the Move: Great Lakes Steal - New Age - Insurgent Steelworker, 1971 (Box 41, Folder 26)
    - Hard Hat News: Hard Hat News, New York, NY, 1989-1998 (Box 41, Folder 27)
    - 65 News: Hilding Anderson Local 65, USWA, AFL-CIO, Chicago, IL, 1980 (Box 41, Folder 28)
    - First Annual Report: Illinois Women's Auxiliary Progressive Miners of America, Springfield, IL, 1933 (Box 172, Folder 1)
    - Independent Gas Flame: Independent Gas Union of the Brooklyn Union Gas Company, Brooklyn, NY, 1941 (Box 44, Folder 8)
    - Coal Strike Continues: Insurgent Miners, 1971 (Box 41, Folder 29)
    - Straight Track: Intercraft Association of Minnesota News: Intercraft Association of Minnesota (ICAM), Minneapolis, MN, 1984-1992 (Box 44, Folder 9)
    - Ironworkers: International Association of Bridge, Structural, Ornamental and Reinforcing Iron Workers, Washington, DC, 2001 (Box 41, Folder 30)
    - IAM Airlines News: International Association of Machinists, 1954 (Box 41, Folder 31)
    - Machinist: International Association of Machinists, 1958-1969 (Box 43, Folder 9)
    - Union Media Monitoring Project: International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers, circa 1970s (Box 41, Folder 32)
    - Turbo-Lines: International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers - Moore Lodge 1580, Wellsville, NY, 1997-2004 (Box 41, Folder 33)
    - Boilermakers-Blacksmiths' Reporter: International Brotherhood of Blacksmiths, Kansas City, KS, 1963-1989 (Box 48, Folder 1-7, Box 84, Folder 1-5, Box 85, Folder 1-4)
    - Boilermaker Reporter: International Brotherhood of Boilermakers, Iron Ship Builders, Blacksmiths, Forgers, and Helpers, AFL-CIO, CFL, Kansas City, KS, 1996 (Box 41, Folder 34)
    - Toll Reporter: International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers - Local Union 1011, San Francisco, CA, 1967 (Box 41, Folder 35)
    - Painters & Allied Trades District Council 9 Spotlight News: International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Tradesmen, New York, NY, 1973-1989 (Box 45, Folder 1)
    - News from the Local: International Federation of Professional and Technical Engineers, Totowa, NJ, 1980 (Box 41, Folder 36)
    - P.A. Chapter News: International Federation of Professional and Technical Engineers (IFPTE) - Engineering & Professional Guild, Local 66, New York, NY, 1979 (Box 41, Folder 37)
    - IMI News: International Masonry Institute, Washington, DC, 1990 (Box 41, Folder 38)
    - International Molders and Allied Workers Union Journal: International Molders and Allied Workers Union, Washington, DC, 1972-1988 (Box 41, Folder 39, Box 174, Folder 1-7)
    - District Three Leader / International Union of Electrical, Radio & Machine Workers: International Union of Electrical, Radio & Machine Workers - District Three, East Rutherford, NJ, 1971-1988 (Box 45, Folder 3-5)
    - Empire State Legislative Bulletin: International Union of Electrical, Radio & Machine Workers - District Three, 1968 (Box 41, Folder 40)
    - Local 103, IUE-CIO Newsletter: International Union of Electronic, Electrical, Salaried, Machine & Furniture Workers, AFL-CIO (IUE) - Local 103, Camden, NJ, 1952 (Box 41, Folder 41)
    - Local 485 News: International Union of Electronic, Electrical, Salaried, Machine & Furniture Workers, AFL-CIO (IUE) - Local 485, Brooklyn, NY, 1957-1984 (Box 45, Folder 6)
    - Independent View: International Union of Elevator Constructors Local 1, 1994 (Box 41, Folder 42)
    - Record: International Union of Operating Engineers - Local 14 & 14B, Flushing, NY, 1975 (Box 41, Folder 43)
    - Local 30 Recorder: International Union of Operating Engineers - Local 30, Richmond Hill, NY, 1986 (Box 41, Folder 44)
    - Engineer: International Union of Operating Engineers - Local 675, Pompano Beach, FL, 1985 (Box 41, Folder 45)
    - IUPIW Views: International Union of Petroleum & Industrial Workers, SIUNA, AFL-CIO, Paramount, CA, 1973-1984 (Box 88, Folder 7)
    - International Woodworker: International Woodworkers of America, Portland, Or, 1978-1987 (Box 46, Folder 1-3)
    - Woodworker: International Woodworkers of America-U.S. (IWA-U.S.) (AFL-CIO), Gladstone, Or, 1987-1993 (Box 46, Folder 4-5)
    - Impact Action: Ironworker Management Progressive Action Cooperative Trust (IMPACT), Washington, DC, 2004 (Box 41, Folder 46)
    - 1026 Rank & File: Local 1026, Hammond, IN, 1980-1981 (Box 41, Folder 47)
    - 475: Local 475, UER & MWA--CIO, Brooklyn, NY, 1947 (Box 41, Folder 48)
    - Local 892 Progressive: Local Union 892 Progressive Club, 1947 (Box 47, Folder 1)
    - Thirtysix: Los Angeles County District Council of Painters 36, Los Angeles, CA, 1987-1994 (Box 47, Folder 2)
    - Engineering News-Record: McGraw-Hill, Inc., New York, NY, 1964 (Box 41, Folder 49)
    - Mentor: Mentor Association, Inc., 1918 (Box 41, Folder 50)
    - Rank & File Unity: Miners' Right to Strike Committee, Beckley, WV, 1976-1977 (Box 47, Folder 3)
    - American Marine Engineer: National Marine Engineers' Beneficial Association AFL-CIO, Washington, DC, 1951-1991 (Box 85, Folder 5-6, Box 86, Folder 1-6)
    - National Steelworkers Rank and File Committee Report: National Steelworkers Rank and File Committee, Lorain, OH, 1976-1979 (Box 173, Folder 20)
    - Bulletin: NY Carpenters for a Stronger Union, circa 1970s (Box 41, Folder 51)
    - Rusty nail: NY Carpenters for a Stronger Union - 608 Chapter, New York, NY, 1983-1988 (Box 41, Folder 52)
    - Voice of United Painters / Published by United Painters and Paperhangers of Greater New York: Painters and Paperhangers Union, New York, NY, 1963-1966 (Box 47, Folder 4)
    - D.C. 9 Newsletter: Painters District Council 9, New York, NY, 1967-1972 (Box 47, Folder 5-6)
    - District Council: Painters District Council 9 of New York City, New York, NY, 1958-1966 (Box 47, Folder 7)
    - Voice: Painters District Council Number 8, San Francisco, CA, 1983 (Box 41, Folder 53)
    - 848er: Painters Rank and File Club - 848, 1947 (Box 41, Folder 54)
    - Painters' Forum: Painters' Trade Union League, New York, NY, 1970 (Box 172, Folder 4)
    - Painting Industry: Painting and Decorating Contractors of America in New York City, Inc., New York, NY, 1956 (Box 41, Folder 55)
    - Paperhanger: Paperhangers Local Union No. 490, 1996 (Box 41, Folder 56)
    - Pig Iron: Pig Iron Press, Youngstown, OH, 1990 (Box 41, Folder 57)
    - Progressive Miner: Progressive Miners of America, Gillespie, IL, 1932-1933 (Box 47, Folder 8)
    - Rank & File Voice: Publicity and Newsletter Committee of the Rank and File Labor Coalition, New York, NY, 1982-1985 (Box 47, Folder 9)
    - Oil Workers News: Published by and for the Employees of the Gulf Oil Corp., Port Arthur, TX, 1941-1942 (Box 47, Folder 10)
    - Hard Hat News: Rank & File Committee Against the 2-Gate, 1987 (Box 41, Folder 58)
    - On the Level: Rank and File Union Carpenters in Northern California, San Francisco, CA, 1989 (Box 41, Folder 59)
    - 1033 News & Views: Republic Steelworkers Local 1033, Chicago, IL, 1972 (Box 41, Folder 60)
    - 1033 Steelworkers Fight Back: Republic Steelworkers Local 1033, 1982 (Box 41, Folder 61)
    - 1971 Steel Strike Showdown: Revolutionary Union, San Francisco, CA (Box 41, Folder 62)
    - Local 483 News: Sheet Metal Workers Local 483, Morrison, TN, 1992 (Box 41, Folder 63)
    - Local 455 News: Shopmen's Local Union, New York, NY, 1963-1969 (Box 47, Folder 11)
    - Spark STEELER: Spark, Baltimore, MD, 1976 (Box 41, Folder 64)
    - Steel Heritage Chronicle: Steel Industry Heritage Task Force, Homestead, PA, 1992 (Box 41, Folder 65)
    - Is He Going to Play With Your Job Next?: Steelworkers for Peurala, circa 1970s (Box 41, Folder 66)
    - Steelworkers On The Move: Steelworkers On The Move, 1976 (Box 41, Folder 67)
    - Struggle in the Coal Fields: Sun Press, Highland Park, MI, 1974 (Box 41, Folder 68)
    - Air Line Mechanic: The Air Line Mechanics Association, Chicago, Il, 1941 (Box 41, Folder 69)
    - 402 Beacon: The Educational Committee of Lodge 402, New York, NY, 1950 (Box 47, Folder 12)
    - Carpenter Magazine: United Brotherhood of Carpenters, Washington, DC, 1989-1998 (Box 42, Folder 1-4, Box 44, Folder 7)
    - Paint Pot: United Coalition of Painters and Allied Trades Committee, New York, NY, 1978 (Box 42, Folder 5)
    - UE Local 417-News: United Electrical and Radio Workers of America - Local 417, Ridgefield Park, NJ, 1978 (Box 42, Folder 6)
    - Sperry News: United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America - Local 450, 1943 (Box 173, Folder 17)
    - United Chemical Worker: United Gas, Coke & Chemical Workers of America, Washington, DC, 1954 (Box 42, Folder 7)
    - Undzer Veg: United Labor Zionist Party of the United States and Canada/Pomer Publishing & Printing Co., New York, NY, 1950 (Box 42, Folder 8)
    - Insurance Career: United Office and Professional Workers of America, New York, NY, 1946 (Box 42, Folder 9)
    - Greater New York Rank & File Painter: United Rank & File Painters of Greater New York/United Rank and File Painters' Social Clubs, D.C. 9, New York, NY, 1939-1948 (Box 47, Folder 13-15)
    - US Steel News: United States Steel Corporation, Pittsburgh, PA, 1982 (Box 42, Folder 10)
    - Aluminum Workers Journal: United Steelworkers of America, New Kensington, PA, 1949 (Box 42, Folder 11)
    - Bulletin: United Steelworkers of America, 1980 (Box 42, Folder 12)
    - Fair Employment Practices in Steel: United Steelworkers of America, Pittsburgh, PA, 1961 (Box 42, Folder 13)
    - Morenci Miners News: United Steelworkers of America, Clifton, AZ, 1984-1984 (Box 42, Folder 14)
    - Steel Worker: United Steelworkers of America, Baltimore, MD, 1977-1977 (Box 47, Folder 16, Box 93, Folder 1-3)
    - Information: United Steelworkers of America - Department of Education, Toronto, Canada, 1962 (Box 42, Folder 15)
    - Local 1010 Steelworker at Inland Steel Company: United Steelworkers of America - Local 1010, East Chicago, IN, 1978-1981 (Box 42, Folder 16, Box 93, Folder 4-5, Box 94, Folder 1-6)
    - 1014 Steelworker: United Steelworkers of America - Local 1014, Gary, IN, 1980 (Box 42, Folder 17)
    - Local 1014 Journal: United Steelworkers of America - Local 1014, Gary, IN, 1981-1985 (Box 42, Folder 18)
    - On Track: United Steelworkers of America - Local 2534, Gary, IN, 1980 (Box 42, Folder 19)
    - 09 Express: United Steelworkers of America - Local 2609, Baltimore, MD, 1981 (Box 42, Folder 20)
    - Rank & File: United Steelworkers of America - Local 2632, Johnstown, PA, 1979 (Box 42, Folder 21)
    - Lockout Bulletin: United Steelworkers of America - Local 5668, Ravenswood, WV, 1992 (Box 42, Folder 22)